Guide to the William J. Baumol Papers, circa 1940-1995 (bulk 1950-1990)
William J. Baumol Papers circa 1940-1995 (bulk 1950-1990)
- Writings Series, 1947-1995
  - 1981-1982 (Box W4)
    - On Inflation and the Arts ( 1982)
    - A Paradox in the Measurement of Interindustry ( 1982)
    - On My Sculptures of Carved Wood ( 1982)
    - Marx and the Iron Law of Wages ( 1982)
    - Deregulation and the New Contestability Analysis ( 1982)
    - Contestable Markets and the Theory of Industry ( 1982)
    - Towards an Analysis of Entrepreneurship ( 1982)
    - Models for Systematic Evaluation of ( 1982)
    - The Income Distribution Frontier ( 1982)
  - 1982-1983 (Box W5)
    - Various ( 1982)
    - Productivity in Higher Education ( 1983)
    - Towards a Theory of Public Enterprise ( 1983)
    - Introduction to Reinecius and Themes that Emerged ( 1983)
    - Fairness Book ( 1983)
    - On the Career of a Microeconomist ( 1983)
    - On Interindustry Differences in Absolute Productivity ( 1983)
    - Feedback Models, R&D, Information ( 1983) (2 folders)
    - Growth Policy and the Services ( 1983)
    - Feedback from Productivity Growth ( 1983)
    - Deregulation and the Theory of Contestable Markets ( 1983)
    - Industry Structure Analysis and Public ( 1983)
    - Various Papers, (1983) (2 folders)
  - 1984-1995 (Box W6)
    - Various Papers, (1984) (2 folders)
    - The Mass Media and the Cost Disease ( 1984)
    - Input and Output Composition Changes ( 1984)
    - On My Attitudes: Sociopolitical and Methodological ( 1984)
    - Use of Antitrust to Subvert Competition and on Productivity Growth in the Long Run ( 1984)
    - Productivity and Related Variables ( 1984)
    - Palgrave Entries ( 1984)
    - Wheatsheaf Prefaces ( 1984)
    - Unbalanced Growth Revisited ( 1984)
    - The Future of the Theatre ( 1984)
    - Rebirth of a Fallen Leader: Italy ( 1985)
    - Productivity Book ( 1986)
    - Chaos: Significance, Mechanism ( 1986)
    - Antitrust Policy and High Technology ( 1988)
    - Antitrust: Source of Dynamic and ... ( 1990)
    - Volume on Entrepreneurship ( 1990)
    - Scale Economies ( 1992)
    - Reswitching, Social Discount Rate, and Environmental Protection ( 1995)
  - Miscellaneous/No Date/and Printed Material (Box W7)
    - Various Papers ( 1968-1979)
    - Various Papers ( 1982-1983)
    - Competitive Interdependence in Decision Making ( undated)
    - Misc. Speeches ( undated)
    - Various Papers ( undated)
    - Publication List ( 1947-1987)
    - Printed Material:
      - C.V. Starr Center Discussion Paper Series ( 1975-1985) (5 folders)
      - An Introduction to Linear Programming
      - Lectures in Economic Theory
      - Superfairness: Applications and Theory
      - Economic Dynamics: An Introduction
      - Business Behavior, Value, and Growth
      - Contestable Markets and the Theory of Industry Structure
- Subject Files Series, 1942-1989
  - Project Files Subseries, 1942-1982
    Includes grants, proposals, reports, and statistical data output. Folder titles are the originals except for the Government, Industry, and Performing Arts files, since most of this material was received as loose papers. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Applied Theory of Fairness ( 1980s) (Box S1)
    - Baumol as Artist ( various dates)
    - Book Proposal: Adventures in Chinese Grocery Shopping ( undated)
    - Committee for Economic Development ( 1982)
    - Committee on Contracting with Publishers ( 1980-1983) (2 folders)
    - Commission on New Technological Uses of Copyrighted Work ( 1976-1977) (2 folders)
    - Cookbook for NSF/DSI ( 1976)
    - Dept. of Agriculture Reports ( 1942-1943 and 1952)
    - Economic Policy Council ( 1970-1974)
    - Government Projects:
      - Joint Economic Committee ( 1958)
      - Senate Judiciary Committee ( 1981)
      - Senate Public Works Committee on Materials Policy ( 1976)
      - Senate Subcommittee on Employment and Productivity ( 1982)
      - State of New York Assembly ( 1984)
      - Subcommittee on the Activities of Regulatory Agencies relating to Small Businesses ( 1968)
      - Telecommunications Bill ( 1982)
      - US House of Representatives ( 1981-1982 and undated)
    - Grants, misc. ( various dates)
    - Industry Consulting:
      - P. Ballatine and Sons ( 1963)
      - Canadian Railroads ( 1976)
      - Carpenter Steel Company ( 1957)
      - Cost Indices ( 1981)
      - Dept. of the Navy ( 1958-1963)
      - General Foods ( 1963)
      - Media Selection ( 1963)
      - Monsanto Chemical Company ( 1957)
      - Morgan Stanley ( 1963-1964) (Box S2)
      - Philadelphia Retail Market ( 1960)
      - Southern Railway ( 1963-1965)
      - Wharton School of Finance and Commerce ( 1960)
    - Interaction between Price Changes and Government Regulation ( 1977)
    - Joint Council on Economic Education ( undated)
    - Lazarsfeld Project ( 1953)
    - Mc Caleb Seiler Publishing Co. ( 1969-70)
    - Microeconomics Research Fund ( 1977-1982) (2 folders)
    - New York University Subcommittee on Graduate Education ( 1983)
    - Performing Arts and Economics:
      - Art Finances ( 1980-1985)
      - Artistic Deficit Study ( 1985-1990) (4 folders)
      - Economic Development and the Performing Arts ( 1982)
      - Financial Data ( 1975-1989)
      - Miscellaneous ( various dates)
      - National Endowment for the Arts ( 1975-1989)
      - Papers ( 1986 and undated)
      - US-USSR Arts Study ( 1989-1990) (4 folders)
    - Pfizer Grant ( 1980-1981)
    - Rescuing the Free Market from its Constituents ( 1983)
    - Scale Economies and Public Attributes of Information ( 1974-1977) (5 folders) (Box S3)
    - Sloan Seminar ( 1978-1982)
    - Towards a Theory of Determination of Market Form ( 1977-1980)
  - Teaching Materials Subseries, 1946-89
    Includes lecture notes, course syllabi, exams and problem sets. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Baumol as Student; includes four undated notebooks
    - Description and Analysis of the Price System ( 1989)
    - Economic Dynamics and Welfare Theory ( 1946-1949)
    - Economics of Antitrust ( 1978)
    - Exams ( 1950-1959)
    - Exams ( 1960-1969)
    - Exams ( 1970-1979)
    - Exams ( 1980-1989)
    - History of Economic Thought ( 1979-1988) (2 folders)
    - Industrial Organization ( undated)
    - Miscellaneous ( various dates)
    - Regulation Lectures ( 1983)
    - Robbins Lectures on Classical Economics ( undated)
    - Transparencies ( undated)
  - Research Files Subseries, undated
    - History of Economics: (Box S4)
      - Cantillon
      - Cournot, A.
      - Marshall, Alfred
      - Marx, Karl (5 folders)
      - Ricardo, David
      - Robbins Manuscript
      - Smith, Adam
      - Wicksell, Knut
    - Industrial Organization:
      - Contestability Theory (5 folders)
      - Predatory Pricing (2 folders)
      - Price Flexibility
    - Fairness (11 folders) (Box S5)
    - Productivity/ Entrepreneurship (3 of 11 folders)
    - Productivity/ Entrepreneurship (folders 4-11) (Box S6)
    - General:
      - Chaos
      - Comparative Statics
      - Current Problems ( undated)
      - Deceleration of British Growth ( 1873-1913) by W. Arthur Lewis ( 1967)
      - Finance
      - Mozart (3 folders)
      - Non Linear Differential Equations
      - Portfolio Theory
- Legal Testimony Series
  Includes sworn testimony, affidavits, drafts, correspondence and papers prepared for counsel. Arranged by date. Material that was clearly marked "privileged and confidential" is noted below; however, without examining every document, it is impossible to conclude that the list is complete or that other documents do not make reference to the confidential material. Researchers wishing to use this series must sign a release form provided by the reference staff.
  - Civil Actions Subseries, 1967-1994 (RESTRICTED)
    - 1967, 5227, Louisville and Nashville Railroad v. United States (Box LT1)
    - 1977, 74C 633, MCI v. AT&T (2 folders)
    - 74-3599 (RJK) and 74-3600 (RJK) USA v. CBS, Inc. and USA v. ABC, Inc.
    - 1981, 74-1698, United States v. AT&T
    - 1981, 79 Civ. 6996, Sharon Steel Corporation
    - 3AN-79-1903 and 3AN-80-1542, Atlantic Richfield Co. v. State of Alaska
    - 82 Civ. 1093 (JES) and 1394, 1737, 2746, 6399 and 83 Civ. 3138 (JES), Low Density Polyethylene Resins Antitrust Litigation (1 folder, 1 bound item)
    - 1984, G-93-265, TCA Building Co. v Northwestern Resources Co. (1 folder, 1 bound item)
    - 1986, Midtec v. C&NW
    - 1987, 86-5428, Chlorine and Caustic Soda Antitrust Litigation (FILED UNDER SEAL)
    - 1988, C.A. no 10319, Grand Metropolitan PLC v. Pillsbury Co.
    - 1989, 88-Civ-3474 (JMcL), City of New York v. US Dept. of Commerce
    - 1989, MDL 587, Lower Lake Erie Iron Ore Antitrust Litigation (2 folders)
    - 1989, MDL-667-ER (TX), Air Passenger Computer Reservation Antitrust Litigation (2 folders, 1 bound item)
    - 1991, 38302s, US Dept. of Energy v. Ohio Railroad Co.
    - 1993, Consolidated Rail Corp.
    - 1994, 82-0192 HHG, USA v. Western Electric and AT&T (2 bound items) (Box LT2)
    - 1994, CV94-3682 (ERK), Bell Atlantic,; NYNEX v. AT&T
  - Federal Communications Commission Subseries, 1966-1994 and undated (RESTRICTED)
    Note: Dockets 16258 are "Qualified Proceedings".
    - 1966-1969, No. 16258
    - 1967, No. 16258, American Telephone and Telegraph Co. ( AT&T)
    - Official Proceedings (7 folders)
    - 1974, AT&T Correspondence (3 folders)
    - 1966-1975, Nos. 16258, 18128, 19919, 20376, 20288, Direct Testimony Exhibits (2 folders)
    - Nos. 18128, 18684, 18718
    - 1976, No. 18128, Memorandum Opinion and Order
    - Circa 1970s, Miscellaneous Testimony
    - 1973-1990, AT&T Papers and Correspondence (Box LT3)
    - 1973-1991, AT&T Papers and Correspondence
    - 1981-1986, AT&T Papers and Correspondence
    - 1983, BC 82-345, Financial Interest Rule and Syndication (1 folder, 2 bound items)
    - 1994, CC Docket 87-313 Policy and Rules Concerning Rates for Dominant Carriers
    - undated, Transparencies
    - undated, Miscellaneous documents
  - Federal Energy Regulatory Commission Subseries, 1983-1993 (RESTRICTED)
    - 1983, OR78-1-014 and 016, TransAlaska Pipeline System
    - 1985, OR79-1-000 and 002, Williams Pipelines Co.
    - 1986, IS85-15-000, Southern Pacific Pipelines, Inc.
    - 1988, IS87-14-000, Buckeye Pipeline Company (PROTECTED MATERIALS)
    - 1993, RM93-11-000, Revisions to Oil Pipeline Regulations
  - Federal Trade Commission Subseries, 1982-1986 (RESTRICTED) (Box LT4)
    - 1982, 9135, B.A.T. Industries and Appleton Papers Inc.
    - 1985, 9157, Echlin Manufacturing Co. and Borg-Warner Corp.
    - 1986, 86-1764, Coca-Cola Company
  - Interstate Commerce Commission Subseries, 1970-1993 and undated (RESTRICTED)
    - 1970, 34013(1), Cost Standards in Intramodal Rate Proceedings
    - 1973, 27353(1), Determination of Compensation (1 folder, 1 bound item)
    - 1980, 9222, Conrail Surcharge on Pulpboard
    - 1981, 37063 and 357, Increased Rates on Coal
    - 1981, No. 30 000, Union Pacific Corp. (2 folders, 1 bound item)
    - 1982-1988, No. 292, Railroad Cost Recovery Procedures (3 bound items)
    - 1982, No. 36988, Alternative Methods of Accounting for Railroad Track Structures
    - 1981-1986, No. 393 (1), Standards for Railroad Revenue Adequacy (1 folder, 4 bound items), cont. in box IV 5
    - 1983, No. 30 300, CSX Corp. v. American Commercial Lines, Inc. (1 folder, 2 bound items) (Box LT5)
    - 1983, No. 347 (1), Coal Rate Guidelines Nationwide (2 folders, 3 bound items), cont. in box 6
    - 1984, No. 30 500, Norfolk Southern Corp. v. North American Van Lines (Box LT6)
    - 1985, No. 445 (1), Intramodal Rail Competition (1 folder, 1 bound item)
    - 1985, No. 346 (8), Exemption from Regulation (2 bound items)
    - 1985, No. 30 400, Sante Fe Southern Pacific Corp. (1 folder; 6 bound items)
    - 1985, No. 456, Staggers Rail Act of 1980
    - 1985, No. 38676
    - 1986, No. 38783, Omaha Public Power v. Burlington Northern Railroad
    - 1985, Chessie Railroad System: Correspondence
    - 1987, Nos. 37809 and 37815s, Burlington Northern Inc., (2 bound items)
    - 1987, No. 38301S, Coal Trading Corp. v. The B&O Railroad Co. (Box LT7)
    - 1987-1994, No. 347(2), Rate Guidelines-Non coal Proceedings (2 bound items)
    - 1990, No. 37063 and 38025s, Rate Reasonableness Issues (1 bound item)
    - 1991, No. 30 000 (16), St. Louis Southwestern Railway (1 folder, 1 bound item)
    - 1992, No. 22218, Atchison, Topeka and Sante Fe Railway Co.
    - 1993, 21215 (5), Seaboard Airline Railroad Co.
    - 1993, 32133(2), Union Pacific (FILED UNDER SEAL)
  - Public Utilities Subseries, 1972-1994 (RESTRICTED)
    - 1972, No. 722-153, Dept. of Public Utilities State of New Jersey
    - 1974, No. 2-U-7423, Public Service Commission of Wisconsin
    - 1975, No. 26775, New York State Public Service Commission (2 folders)
    - 1985, Nos. 86-2, 85-186, 85-212, State of Maine Public Utilities Commission (5 folders)
    - 1985, No. TC-85-126, TO-85-130 and TO-84-223, Public Service Commission of the; State of Missouri (Box LT8)
    - 1987, PUC 870012, Virginia State Corporation Commission
    - 1988, Nos. 87-0169, 87-0427, 88-0189, 88-0219, 83-0537, and 84-0555, Illinois Commerce Commission
    - 1989, No. 6669, Public Utilities Commission of Texas (2 folders)
    - 1992, No. I.87-11-033, Public Utilities Commission of California
    - 1994, Nos. 93-576-TP-CSS and 93-487-TP-ALT, Public Utilities Commission of Ohio
    - Miscellaneous papers, various dates
  - Tax Court Subseries, 1982-1991 and undated (RESTRICTED)
    - 1982, No. 12836-79, G. D. Searle and Co.
    - 1987, No. 26230-83, Sunstrand Corp. and Subsidiaries
    - 1991, No. 28860-89, Perkin-Elmer Corp.
    - undated, Nos. 2674-88 and 23619-88, Yamaha Motor Corp.
  - Miscellaneous, 1973-1994 and undated (RESTRICTED)
    - Postal Rate Commission (2 folders)
    - 1983, No. 41686, Civil Aeronautics Board
    - 1984-1985, Computer Inquiry Project (3 folders) CONFIDENTIAL (Box LT9)
    - 1985 and undated, Fidelity Management and Research Co./Brokerage Commission Rates (3 folders) CONFIDENTIAL
    - 1985, Railroad Accounting Principles Board (1 folder, 1 bound item)
    - 1986, No. 29469, AT&T Communications of New York
    - 1994, New Zealand Telecom
    - Undated, Nos. 88-07-020, 88-08-051, 89-03-046, AT&T Communications of California
    - Undated, Copyright Royalty Tribunal
    - Undated, DPU 18210, New England Telephone and Telegraph Co. (2 folders)
    - undated, Misc. Testimony and Papers (3 folders) Some FILED UNDER SEAL
    - Printed Material:
      - Hearings before a subcommittee of the Committee on Appropriations, House of Representatives; Subcommittee on HUD independent agencies
      - Hearings before the Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate on Monopolization and Competition in the Telecommunications Industry
      - Hearings before the Subcommittee on Telecommunications, Consumer Protection, and Finance of the Committee on Energy and Commerce; House of Representatives
- Accession 2001-0169, 1964-1990s
  Boxes 2-3 and 12-14 contain sensitive material. Patron must sign a release form before use. Contact a Reference Archivist.
  - Lectures and reserve materials for Economics 506: History of Economic Thought, Economics 541: Industrial Organization and Public Policy, and Economics 102: Micro-Description and Analysis of Price Systems, 1979; Reviews and comments, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Warhol case, NZ, Misc. Cons[ultations], 1991-1995 (Box 2-3)
    Includes sensitive information: legal case files. Patron must sign privacy waiver before use.
  - 6th ed. Baumol-Blinder, 1992 (Box 3-5)
    Correspondence and drafts of each chapter of Economics: Principles and Policy
  - Drafts of articles, 1982-1994 (Box 5-7)
    Also includes biographical information in box 6.
  - Expired grants, 1986-1990 (Box 7-9)
    Mainly Pew Charitable Trust and National Science Foundation.
  - Drafts of essays, newspaper articles, and speeches; book reviews written by Baumol, 1973-1992 (Box 9-11)
  - Drafts of articles, 1986-1990s (Box 12-14)
    Includes testimony for air passenger computer reservation systems antitrust litigation case in box 12.
  - Correspondence, 1964-1978; reviews of Baumol's work and his comments, 1979-1980 and 1974 (Box 15-17)
  - Miscellaneous Baumol/Wolff/Blackman productivity articles, 1979-1988 (Box 17-21)
  - Productivity files (old), 1981-1985 (Box 21-23)
    Including "Sue Anne's Files."
  - Files (drafts), 1989-1993 (Box 24-26)
    Includes drafts of essays and newspaper articles.
  - [Drafts of chapters for] Productivity and American Leadership: The Long View (Box 26-28)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1986-1987; reviews and comments file, 1985-1995 (Box 28-32)
  - Legal-size materials (Box 32)
    - Warhol case materials
    - Convergence of productivity Baumol art
- Accession 2001-0170, 1974-1990
  Boxes 1, 5-7 contain sensitive material. Patron must sign a release form before use. Contact a Reference Archivist.
  - Sloan applicants; articles reviewed or read; recommendations, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
    Contains sensitive material. Patron must sign release form before use. Contact a Reference Archivist.
  - Recommendations, 1975-1981; engagements accepted and not accepted, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
  - Includes possible study and leave opportunities; the World Resources Institute; and engagements accepted and not accepted, 1985-1990 (Box 3)
  - Includes engagements accepted, 1990; New York University economics department interoffice memoranda, budgets, and other correspondence; and Eastern Economic Association correspondence and other materials, 1977-1985 (Box 4)
  - Includes New York University economics department forms, tenure material, and other material, 1974-1982; correspondence with and manuscripts from Harcourt, Brace, Jonanovitch, Inc., 1982-1985; correspondence, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Includes recommendations, 1988-1989; proposals, books, and articles reviewed, 1981-1989; graduate student correspondence, salary information, and other materials from Princeton University, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Includes material for On Finances of the Performing Arts During Stagflation, 1980-1982; and National Science Foundation proposals reviewed and other NSF materials, 1981-1984 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and material relating to Baumol's work on Fritz Machlup's book, 1982-1984; drafts of articles written for various journals, including the Journal of Political Economy, Journal of Law and Economics, and Journal of Economic Literature, 1976-1990 (Box 8)
  - Computer Diskettes containing graphs, publications, miscellaneous information, and system software (Box 9)
    [Electronic records are closed to use until migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Reel-to-reel audiotape: Velocidad Grabación-3 3/4, miércoles 11 de enero de 1978 [1978 Jan 11 Wed.], 15 minutos del día 12 Lado 2 [15 minutes of day 12, side 2] (Box 10)
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]